Guide to the Abortion Rights Association, Inc., photographs and pamphlets, 1972-1974 and undated RL.11371
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abortion Rights Association, Inc., photographs and pamphlets
1972-1974 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abortion Rights Association of New York. Medical Responsibilities Committee
Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
RL.11371
1.0 Linear Feet
Seven mounted photographs and five pamphlets from the Abortion Rights Association of New York, later known as the Abortion Rights Association, Inc., dating between 1972 and 1974. Pamphlets explain abortion procedures, clinic and physician guidelines, and women's rights to abortion, largely designed to address and implement the Supreme Court decision Roe v. Wade. Photographs (which contain captions) include black-and-white images of tools used in self-induced abortions; coroner's office photographs of deceased women following self-induced abortions; morgue photographs of infanticide victims; and images of fetuses in utero.
Biographical / Historical
The Abortion Rights Association of New York, later known as the Abortion Rights Association, Inc., was based in New York City and advocated for women's rights to legal access to medical abortions. The group published several pamphlets outlining women's rights to abortion and listing abortion providers in New York State.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Abortion Rights Association, Inc., photographs and pamphlets were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from Lisa Baskin in 2015.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of a set of seven mounted photographs, apparently intended for exhibition, and a set of five pro-choice pamphlets created by the Abortion Rights Association of New York (later known as Abortion Rights Association, Inc.). The photographs include coroner's office photographs of deceased women following self-inflicted abortions; morgue photographs of infanticides; equipment and tools used in self-inflicted abortions; and fetuses in utero, one with deformed brain. Author of the included captions is unknown. The pamphlets, written to assist New York physicians and practioners implementing the Supreme Court Roe v. Wade ruling, address women's rights to clinical abortions, abortion laws, counseling and guidance on policies, and references to New York abortion clinics and practitioners.
General
Forms part of the Lisa Unger Baskin Collection. Lisa Baskin noted that she originally received these items from Dr. Thomas Plaut, a member of the Medical Responsibilities Committee in the Abortion Rights Association of New York.
Abortion -- Law and legislation; Abortion services -- New York (State); Abortion -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Abortion -- Pictorial works; Infanticide -- Pictorial works; Fetus -- Physiology -- Pictorial works; Baskin, Lisa Unger, former owner; Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Pamphlets, 1972-1974 (Folder 1)
  - "Listing of Selected New York State Abortion Clinics." Issued by Medical Responsibilities Committee of the Abortion Rights Association of New York, 1972 (Folder 1)
  - "Abortion: Guidelines for Counseling. To Implement the Supreme Court Abortion Decisions." Abortion Rights Association, Inc., 1973 (Folder 1)
  - "Abortion: A Physician's Rights and Responsibilities. To Implement the Supreme Court Abortion Decisions." Issued by the Medical Responsibilities Committee of Abortion Rights Association, Inc., 1973 (Folder 1)
  - "Abortion: A Woman's Right. To Implement the Supreme Court Abortion Decisions." Abortion Rights Association, Inc., 1973 (Folder 1)
  - "Effects of New York State's Liberalized Abortion Law. To Implement the Supreme Court Abortion Decisions." Abortion Rights Association, Inc., 1974 (Folder 1)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - A1. "Woman dead on motel room floor from air embolism during criminal abortion. From files of Dr. Milton Helpern, Medical Examiner, New York City", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-001)
  - A2. "Anencephalic fetus in utero, about 1 1/2 months; a deformity characterized by a gross malformation in which the brain extends beyond the skull. From files of Dr. Chester Swinyard, Institute of Rehabilitation Medicine, New York University Medical Center", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-002)
  - A3. "Infanticide victim, photographed on newspaper, was discovered on tenement steps. From files of Dr. Milton Helpern, Medical Examiner, New York City", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-003)
  - A4. "Weapons used in self-abortion include coat hanger; knitting needle; catheter, or rubber tube; bulb syringe; and lysol, a corrosive solution. These materials are forced into the uterus to dislodge the fetus", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-004)
  - A5. "Group photo of turtle (1), mouse (2), human (3), chick (4), and pig (5) at a comparable developmental age. Radiologist Dr. Roberts Rugh took the picture, which stresses the similarity, to challenge the contention of some that the fetus is a human person from the moment of conception. Says Rugh: 'It is not a viable human being until it can survive the major transition of birth, by whatever means, at about seven months.'", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-005)
  - B1. "Woman dead on bathroom floor from self-induced lye abortion; mother of three; found by husband. Photo from Coroner's Office, Hennepin County, Minnesota", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-006)
  - B2. "Infanticide victim, burned in incinerator, then discarded in snowbank; found by two children on their way to school. Photographed in County Morgue, Hennepin County, Minnesota", undated (Box 1, Print RL-11371-P-007)